A Guide to the Papers of Joseph L. Bishop, 1973-1982
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Joseph L. Bishop 1973-1982
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13953
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift from the Estate of Joseph L. Bishop, through Susan M. Bishop, to the University of Virginia Library on September 6, 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joe Bishop was a well known local promoter of conservatism and libertarianism in Charlottesville, Virginia. He was the secretary of the Charlottesville Republican Committee and the State Chairman of the Virginia Chapter of Young Americans for Freedom (1977). He graduated from the University of Virginia in 1974 and was a life long member of the Jefferson Literary and Debating Society.
The Young Americans for Freedom, a conservative youth organization, was founded in September 1960 at the Sharon, Connecticut, estate of William F. Buckley, Jr. and developed a set of governing principles called the "Sharon Statement." The organization sponsors programs and conferences that campaign against "big government" and offers support for the rights of individuals. Its main publications are the New Guard and Dialogue on Liberty.
Scope and Content
The Papers of Joseph L. Bishop, 1973-1982, consist chiefly of materials relating to Young Americans for Freedom, both the national body and the University of Virginia Chapter and contain: board meeting minutes; by-laws; certificates; conference materials; correspondence, including a routine letter from Governor Mills E. Godwin; financial information; membership information; news clippings; literature about projects; information from the regional, state and national levels of the Young Americans for Freedom; some material from the UVA chapter and political buttons. There are also political buttons that are housed separately. The collection contains 590 items in two Hollinger boxes (1.25 linear feet).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Bishop- Personal, 1971-1973, 4 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Political identification cards.
- Blue Ridge- Young Americans for Freedom, 1977, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:2)
- By-laws and certificates, 1970-1977, 11 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Conference- Annual Young Americans for Freedom, San Francisco, 1974 July 18-21, 11 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Conference- Conservative Political Action, Washington D. C., 1975 February 13-16, 13 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Conference- Southern Regional Young Americans for Freedom, Charlottesville, Virginia, 1975 March 21-23, 14 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Conference- 9th National Convention of Young Americans for Freedom, Madison Square Garden, New York, 1977 August 24-28, 8 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Correspondence, 1975-1977, 21 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Includes a discussion about discontinuing the publication, New Guard; mentions controversies about particular members; and information about the Allan Bakke reverse discrimination case.
- Financial, 1972-1977, 24 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
- General Assembly, 1974-1976, 4 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Membership, 1972-1980, 72 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
- National-Young Americans for Freedom, 1975-1982, 36 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
- News clippings, 1975-1977, 22 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Operation Salvation- Solzhenitsyn, 1974, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Press Releases, 1973-1977; n. d., 16 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Projects, 1974-1980; n. d., 34 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Projects, literature, news letters and flyers, 1974-1977; n. d., 69 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Scholarships, n. d., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
- State and Regional- Young Americans for Freedom, 1971-1976, 45 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
- State and Regional- Young Americans for Freedom, 1977-1980, 42 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  Including a financial statement and newsletters.
- State and Regional- Young Americans for Freedom, n. d., 44 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
- University of Virginia- Young Americans for Freedom, 1970-1980; n. d., 74 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Zero Government Growth, 1976; n. d., 26 items. (Box-folder 2:8)